<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="yes"?>

<story><div id="foreword"><h1>2.  The Alchemist</h1> <p1>The chronology of the industrial process (the writing of this novel) demands we move to the next step and perform its manufacture. From our previous analogy, The Burn, we carry with us a motivating force, that alchemists would have called 'the vulgar fire' and they offered the figure of Vulcan as representative of that element. </p1> <p>The alchemist <citation>(name)Smith(date)1990(pages)30</citation> Francis Bacon stands Vulcan next to another important figure, Daedalus. 'Vulcan or Daedalus (that is, the furnace or engine)' (Bacon, 1905: 423). Daedalus means 'cunning worker' and if Vulcan is the burn, then Daedalus is the engine. This is our urgent wish now, to get on and make. This impatience, the desire to rush into print, is a feature of the novelist's character, generally (Smith, 1990: 80; Jones, 2001: 90) speaking and especially (Jones, 2001: 90) the apprentice novelist.</p> <p>E. E. Cummings advises us that writers are people 'who are obsessed by Making' (Herbert and Hollis, 2000: 53), and the analogy I will invoke in order to explore the manufacture of fiction is that of the writer-as-alchemist.</p> <p>I first followed this train of thought&#x2013;the writer-as-alchemist&#x2013;when the critic Fiammetta Rocco wrote a review of my novel, <i>The Unnumbered</i> (2004) in <i>The Economist</i> (29 April 2004). It contained a phrase that naturally I seized on; she suggested the novel ' ...  should be read by anyone who believes in the transforming power of fiction'. </p> <p>It became one of those phrases that cropped up everywhere. I could not listen to a literary commentary without hearing it expounded. But what did she mean&#x2013;what was this 'transforming power' of fiction? I understood it to be a transformation of the reader&#x2013;at the very least a temporary, sensual transformation. The reader would approach the fiction in one state, would read the work, and be transformed by its processes into another state. </p> <p>The question was: transformed from what, to what? From a lower to a higher position, I was sure: from relative ignorance to knowledge and truth, from confusion and cloudiness to understanding and clarity. The reader would be walked forward a pace or two in the dawdle that is one's growing, progressive conception of what life is and what it should be. And to wreak this kind of effect on a reader is the ambition of writers, so that a novel of theirs might become a milestone in the reader's consciousness, part of the fabric of its expansion. </p> <p>But how was a novel supposed to do this? It is clear that a factual text can do the same thing: to read a particular history, for instance Misha Glenny's description of the globalization of crime, <i>McMafia</i> (2008/2009), or to read a book about the feathered edges of the human brain's behaviour, such as Oliver Sacks' <i>The Man Who Mistook His Wife for a Hat</i> (1985/2007), is to have one's perception transformed. </p> <p>The writer of fiction aims to achieve the same ascension of the reader, but by virtue of making it up, by inventing. Therefore, an additional kind of transformation is required: the ingredients of life (i.e. reality) must first be assembled and thereafter manipulated before they can be transformed into fiction. In order to create in readers, in their turn, a transformative epiphany. </p> <p>There is something of the magician, the alchemist, in the person who can perform this 'pleasant and sportive fiction of the transformation of bodies' (Bacon, 1905: 822), who can manipulate the base materials of life, apply pressure to them, until they are transformed and given extraordinary value. </p> <p>Why alchemists, and not chemists? Alchemy, after all, is an outmoded science; it was the precursor of chemistry; the adepts at alchemy lacked knowledge and resorted to bluster and pretence and magic and lying. Raymond Lully, a relatively recent adept, was apparently hired by Edward II and shown to a workbench in the Tower of London where he transmuted from base metal 50,000 pounds worth of gold coins, which were used to help finance the Crusades. Afterwards he went on to live to the age of one hundred and fifty, all the while able to run and jump like a youth. </p> <p>There was no limit to the ambition, the bluster and the myth-making. The alchemist Artephius, in his <i>The Art of Prolonging Human Life</i> (circa 1200), claimed that he had ' ...  now lived one thousand years or thereabouts' (www.alchemylab.com, 2010).</p> <p>Alchemy liked to pretend that it was chemistry. Surely, in the modern day, the writer-as-chemist would be more consistently successful, more accurate, more true, than the writer-as-alchemist? </p> <p>Johann Wolfgang von Goethe was successful both as a scientist and as a writer. He wrote a novel, <i>Elective Affinities</i> (1809), which proposed that chemistry underpinned human psychological behaviour. The novel's opening thesis is that we react with one another like chemicals, either attracting each other (in the case of people who do have an affinity), or repelling one another (in the case of those who do not). Meanwhile the insertion of character C to the mix of characters A and B might cause A and B to split asunder, and A and C to join together causing B to be ejected on its own. </p> <p>This is the fate of Charlotte (in Goethe's novel) when she and her husband, Eduard, invite the Captain to stay on their estate for an extended period. Immediately on his arrival the Captain forms an energetic friendship with Eduard and Charlotte is left to her own devices. All three happily compare themselves to chemical substances and reactions. 'What we call limestone,' says the Captain, 'is a more or less pure oxide of calcium tightly combined with a weak acid known to us in gaseous form. If a piece of that rock is placed in dilute sulphuric acid this combines with the calcium to form gypsum; the gaseous weak acid, on the other hand, escapes' (Goethe, 1809/1994: 33).</p> <p>Charlotte objects to being 'that poor creature' (Goethe, 1809/1994: 33), the gaseous vapour which escapes and is left on its own. As she points out, it 'may have a great deal to put up with' (Goethe, 1809/1994: 33).</p> <p>It is proposed that a fourth character is added to the mixture, so that Charlotte will not be lonely. Together they decide on Ottilie, her orphaned niece, as the new ingredient. The Captain suggests, ' ...  now bring the pairs into contact; A will go over to D, C to B, without our being able to say who first left the other' (Goethe, 1809/1994: 34). The Captain and Ottilie will get together, both being single and unattached, and Eduard will thus be thrown back together in the company of his wife.</p> <p>Their amiable analysis does not work out. It is the husband, Eduard, who is forcibly attracted to Ottilie, while Charlotte becomes intensely involved with the Captain. The quartet&#x2013;and especially the marriage&#x2013;is put under unbearable strain. </p> <p>What is most remarkable in this plain-speaking novel is the chaotic nature of its emotional progression. The science of chemistry is valued at the start of the text, but, as the situation develops, a more powerful force becomes evident&#x2013;alchemy. With Eduard at the height of his enchantment with Ottilie, and his wife, Charlotte, enthralled by the Captain, Eduard happens to find himself outside his wife's bedroom door and knocks for admittance. 'Her first thought was that, “it might, it must be the Captain”' but she is wrong, it is her husband, who says, 'I have vowed I shall kiss your shoe before the morning' (Goethe, 1809/1994: 78). </p> <p>Both are in the grip of a passionate attachment to another person, but here the husband and wife find their way to each other by accident, and while they seduce each other they imagine those others by whom they are captivated. 'By lamplight, then, in a twilight, the heart's desires and the imagination at once asserted their rights over reality. Eduard held Ottilie in his arms; now closer, now receding, the Captain hovered before Charlotte's soul; and thus absent and present in the queerest fashion were intermingled, in excitement and delight' (Goethe, 1809/1994: 79).</p> <p>More importance is attached by the characters in the story to the province of the imagination, than to the science of reality. Signifiers of fate begin to exert a powerful influence. A glass, which by chance happens to be engraved with the initials of Eduard and Ottilie, is thrown into the air during a ceremony to mark the laying of the foundation stone of a new house built on the estate, and ordinarily it would have fallen and smashed but someone on the scaffold caught the glass and so it never fell. At great cost Eduard buys it, and he drinks from it every day to re-affirm his hopes for a relationship with Ottilie. '[I]n the uncertainty of life,' begs Eduard, 'leave a heart struggling between hope and fear at least some sort of guiding star that it can look to, even if not steer by' (Goethe, 1809/1994: 113). </p> <p>The alchemical influences proliferate. A visiting gentleman and his companion notice Ottilie's illogical aversion to a particular pathway on the estate and want to try an experiment. ' ...  I cannot possibly leave here without having that beautiful child try the oscillations too' (Goethe, 1809/1994: 195). They set out the 'golden rings, marcasites, and other metallic substances' (Goethe, 1809/1994: 195), and first Charlotte and then Ottilie suspend the pendulum over the array of ingredients. With Charlotte there is no result, but with Ottilie, ' ...  at once the dangling metal was seized, really as if in a whirlpool, and veered to one side or the other, according to what new substances were placed below, now in a circle, now in straight lines, just as the gentleman's companion might have hoped, in a way exceeding all his hopes' (Goethe, 1809/1994: 196).</p> <p>One could not ask for a more scientific writer than Goethe yet it is alchemy that he invokes in his manufacture of fiction precisely because of its bluster, its downright lying and illusion-making&#x2013;in other words, its magic. These qualities of magic are inherent in alchemy: the altering of the appearance of the ingredients, the changing of the onlooker's perception, the obstruction, the deliberate hiding of the truth. The self-delusion, the trickery of alchemy are more aligned to the behaviour of the human mind, deep in its own cave, than the always-predictable, immutable processes of chemistry. </p> <p>In short, chemistry is physical while alchemy is metaphysical; and the novel is a metaphysical creature. </p> <p>Kundera saw what the problem was. 'But how can <i>uncontrolled</i> imagination be integrated into the novel,' he asked, 'which by definition is supposed to be a lucid examination of existence? How can such disparate elements be united? That calls for a real alchemy!' (Kundera, 1986/2005: 83).</p> <p>The alchemists, in their earliest manifestation, claimed it was an art that translated the inferior into the superior, that it was capable of transforming a mundane material, usually a common metal, into a valuable one&#x2013;often gold. Francis Bacon tells us about a certain Sir Edward Dyer who travelled all the way to Germany to observe 'Kelley the alchemist'.  On Dyer's return he hastened to the dinner table of the Lord of Canterbury  to report what he had seen, and </p> <blockquote><p> ...  turning to <i>the</i> Archbishop,</p><p> [he] said ; <i>... I saw Master Kelley put of the base metal into the crucible, and after it was set a little upon the fire, and a very small quantity of the medicine put in, and stirred with a stick of wood, it came forth in great proportion perfect gold, to the touch, to the hammer, to the test</i>. (Bacon, 1905: 886)</p></blockquote> <p_after_extract class='hello'>Today&#x2013;especially given the Internet&#x2013;it is still easy to find those who are excited to believe all these stories are true: a certain Reginald Merton, for instance, in an article on the Alchemy Lab website (http://www.alchemylab.com/history_of_alchemy.htm) lists an army of alchemists and what he believes to have been their certain, proven achievements, 'Raymond Lully made gold for the King of England. George Ripley gave a hundred thousand pounds of alchemical gold to the Knights of Rhodes ... Gustavus Adolphus of Sweden had an enormous number of gold pieces coined ... by an unknown man under the protection of the king'. Reginald argues that 'Only a very few adepts knew of the essential agent, the sublime heat of the soul, which fuses the emotions, consumes the prison of leaden form and allows entry into the higher world'.</p_after_extract> <p>The connection with myth making and deception means that my figure of the writer-as-alchemist is a close cousin to Lewis Hyde's trickster. In his long excavation of this cultural figure, <i>Trickster Makes This World</i> (1998), Hyde describes the trickster as, 'master of the kind of creative deception that, according to a long tradition, is a pre-requisite of art' (Hyde, 2008: 17).</p> <p>The writer-as-alchemist, therefore, is my analogy, and this its thesis: that the manufacture of fiction requires the writer to take the base materials of life, whether they are unusual or commonplace, and either turn them into gold, or make with them the Philosopher's Stone, or mix them to concoct the elixir of life. </p> <p>How do we prepare ourselves for this task and how do we train ourselves in this art? </p> <p>The work of the alchemist is to find and gather ingredients, then to mix and process them, or separate them out and keep them apart, subtly manipulate the elements, apply intense pressure, create explosions, conjure up magical transformations, hide trickery, manufacture bluff and thereby create belief, in order to make something apparently of great value and thus fiction extends its promise, to transform. </p> <h2>1. Gathering</h2> <p1>Our first task is to harvest materials or ingredients; this is the essential (even if unconscious) precursor to the fictive process. </p1> <p>For <i>What The Children Saw</i> I will gather up memories of my children's imaginative games. We have all been children and know the common sights: the sheets and blankets thrown over sofas and chairs to make a den, the understairs cupboard transformed into a cave, the camp built of branches and foliage in the garden, the tower made of bricks, the toy cars parked in rows. They are evidence of children making up stories for themselves. The duration and intensity of such imaginative games confirm the compulsive attraction of storytelling.</p> <p>I have fifteen years of such memories (in later years seeing only glimpses, overheard from a distance, because with older children an adult presence brings shame and breaks the spell) and I wish to construct for both the adult and the child reader a similar experience, of entering a game&#x2013;a story&#x2013;that is so compelling one never wishes to leave. So my base materials are both pedestrian and magical at the same time.</p> <p>How does the novelist then take these base materials and make them valuable? It is the same question, in <i>A Portrait of the Artist as a Young Man</i> (1916), that Stephen asks the Dean, 'What is that beauty which the artist struggles to express from lumps of earth' (Joyce, 1916/2000: 154)? </p> <p>We have our base materials: a scruffy assembly of ingredients, inert, but full of possibility, imbued with emotions as yet unrealized. So&#x2013;what next?</p> <h2>2. Mixing together</h2> <p1>Carol Shields starts her novel <i>The Stone Diaries</i> with a recipe for Malvern pudding and this puts her text on the right footing immediately for the purposes of this analogy. The mixture of ingredients&#x2013;and also how you grind them, to get at the detail, how you stir them, heat them, apply pressure to them in order to join them together&#x2013;is the issue here.</p1> <p>First of all we have one fat, greedy woman. 'Mercy Stone weighs forty stone' (Shields, 1993/2008: 33) was chanted as a skipping rhyme by the foundlings at the orphanage where Mercy Goodwill was brought up, and we learn that 'Eating was as close to heaven as my mother ever came' (Shields, 1993/2008: 1).  Mixed with her, attached to her, is the opposite quality in her husband, Cuyler Goodwill, a slender male, 'short of stature, small-boned and neat' (Shields, 1993/2008: 17), also described as 'a runt' (Shields, 1993/ 2008: 24) and, to complement her appetite, he is a dainty eater even though he works in a quarry, 'A pick-and-nibble fellow, she calls him, able to take his food or leave it' (Shields, 1993/2008: 1).</p> <p>Opposites attract. The minus qualities in his character are fixing strongly to the positive values in hers. The glue is irony. </p> <p>I can immediately seize on this, and use the shape of it for <i>What The Children Saw.</i> In the first part of <i>The Stone Diaries</i> Carol Shields brings us to the birth of her narrator and I, too, want to bring someone to life. But <i>What The Children Saw</i> is an Easter story; I want to bring my character back from the dead. It is the story of the resurrection  of a deceased grandparent.</p> <p>I have two houses, on either side of the graveyard. What if, in one house, there are plenty of grandparents available, and therefore a rich supply of Easter eggs, while on the other side, there is none? No grandparents, because they are all dead and gone. Now I have to think how it could work the other way: in order to tie these two sets of children together in an ironic double-bond, what could the children without grandparents <i>have</i>, which their neighbours <i>don't</i> have?</p> <p>To look for any possible answer, I continue to read <i>The Stone Diaries</i> and find more ironic oppositions arranged in her characters. Cuyler Goodwill is sexually charged. 'The tidal motion of sexual longing filled him to the brim' (Shields, 1993/2008: 33) and 'he wants to bury himself in her exalting abundance' (Shields, 1993/2008: 34) whereas Mercy is sexually inert. ' ...  he knew that Mercy Stone's ardour was of a quality inferior to his own' (Shields, 1993/2008: 34) reports the narrator, Daisy, and she goes on to describe how 'The potency and fragrance of erotic love that overwhelmed him in his twenty-sixth year was answered by Mercy with mild bewilderment' (Shields, 1993/2008: 33). The 'minus' in her connects with the 'plus' in him.</p> <p>What other ingredients are selected? There is quite a collection of things in that cavernous belly of Mercy's. Although the Malvern pudding itself, the stale bread and the sweet blackcurrants, 'A warm sponge soaking up color' (Shields, 1993/2008: 2) will not make it, there is plenty of other stuff that does go in. 'One day, alone in the kitchen, she consumed an entire loaf between noon and supper' (Shields, 1993/2008: 6). And, 'she imagines the soft dough entering the bin of her stomach, lining that bitter bloated vessel with a cottony warmth' (Shields, 1993/2008: 6).</p> <p>There is not only food in that stomach, but pain and discomfort, caused possibly by indigestion. At night 'she's risen from her sleep and dosed herself with Bishop's Citrate of Magnesia' (Shields, 1993/2008: 5). And there is more pain and discomfort. 'Her abdominal walls have continued to cramp and heave all spring ...  She experiences scalding attacks of flatulence, especially at night' (Shields, 1993/2008: 6).</p> <p>Carol Shields has made the woman huge, and the things in her belly become huge as well&#x2013;the food, the hunger, the pain, the flatulence, and of course, the most important thing of all&#x2013;the narrator, Daisy, a foetus about to be born.</p> <p>Another recipe&#x2013;another mixture of ingredients to which careful processes have been applied&#x2013;is the cast of characters recruited to witness this birth: 'Life is an endless recruiting of witnesses. It seems we need to be observed in our postures of extravagance or shame, we need attention paid to us' (Shields, 1993/2008: 36).</p> <p>The newly weds, Mercy and Cuyler, are given neighbours who are at the other end of the childbirth tunnel. Mrs Flett is 'half-crazed by menopause and loneliness' (Shields, 1993/2008: 37) and she is fed up with her husband's advances ...  'I am not willing' (Shields, 1993/2008: 16) she imagines saying to him, to deflect his unromantic, prosaic demands for sex, while she listens, jealously, to Mercy's husband saying how much he loves her.  'I love you,' she heard young Cuyler Goodwill say to his immense, bloated wife, Mercy. 'Oh how I love you, and with all my heart.' (Shields, 1993/2008: 16).</p> <p>If Mercy has something that Clarentine Flett longs for, then the reverse is also true. Mercy wants nothing more than the cold box given to Clarentine by <i>her</i> husband. Each has something the other wants&#x2013;like a double hand clasp&#x2013;and the joinery used again is irony. (Shields frequently uses irony to bind together her ingredients. Later on, in the two sets of letters written on pages 50–8, while one correspondent thanks Cuyler for providing money, the other correspondent, Marcus Flett, is begging his father to send money.) </p> <p>On the day of the birth of the narrator, a character called 'the old Jew' enters stage left, with his 'high-pitched yipping' (Shields, 1993/2008: 19). He is a picture of madness in this sane, almost suburban setting and it adds that note of danger to the proceedings. 'The voice is demented; it has the creak of terror in it' (Shields, 1993/2008: 21).</p> <p>Carol Shields has also stirred another set of ingredients into this opening sequence: the past, present and future. The future, in the shape of the narrator, Daisy, who has travelled back in time to describe things she cannot possibly have seen or known about&#x2013;among them, her own birth. An imagined future is Cuyler's hardly dared-for dream of having children and 'a more commodious house, lit in the evenings with brighter lamps' (Shields, 1993/2008: 35). The present and the future are wrapped together in the shape of Mercy's cooking of the Malvern pudding which the narrator has the authority to withdraw from us at the end, using past, present and future tenses: 'Where, you ask, is the Malvern pudding, weighted with its ancient stone? It has been set aside, as has my mother's cookery book. They will not be seen again in this story' (Shields, 1993/2008: 38). The present is also evident in Cuyler's walk back home from work to confront the scene of his wife's labour, and in the cast of characters 'invited to participate in a moment of history. History indeed! As though this paltry slice of time deserves such a name. Accident, not history, has called us together, and what an assembly we make' (Shields, 1993/2008: 39). And the past is there, in the extensive telling of Mercy's lack of history, her upbringing in the foundling home, and in the convincing portrayal of Cuyler's past, 'the chill and meagreness of his parents' house' (Shields, 1993/2008: 28).</p> <p>Thus it seems like all of time itself is brought together for this exact moment, which she describes as a 'clamour of inadequacy and portent,' to witness whatever comes out of the mixture of ingredients which have been mashed up together in Mercy's stomach.</p> <p>The grip (with irony the atomic force that binds the elements) creates an inward pressure, and the tighter the elements are bound together the more it loads up the force of the explosion to come.</p> <p>And yet how disparate and conflicting is this mixture Carol Shields has concocted&#x2013;she seems to admit, 'I long to bring symmetry to the various discordant elements' (Shields, 1993/2008: 23)&#x2013;but of course, in this instance as in so many others in this novel (when she pretends to observe her own birth, when she puts fake photographs in the middle of the book to increase its authority as an autobiography), the author is a liar. She does not 'long to bring symmetry' at all, she has deliberately chosen such discordant elements. Indeed, they are her chosen form of symmetry. </p> <p>And I have left until last the biggest opposites that she arranges together: the oil and the water, the two that never can mix&#x2013;life and death. She presses them up against each other just as tightly as she possibly can, 'the clout of death and the wriggling foolishness of birth' (Shields, 1993/2008: 40). She bangs their heads together, in one sharp instant, to give this story its life. Mercy will die in the act of childbirth.</p> <p>The art of alchemy defines one of its processes as exhalation&#x2013;the escape of a gas, an invisible thing, from the mixture. Carol Shields grinds up her mixture, and achieves this exhalation. In order to create (literally out of the last breath of the dying Mercy) the beginning of the story, the birth of the narrator in this <i>faux</i> autobiography, she writes:</p> <blockquote><p>It's this wing-beat of breath I reach out for. Even now I claim it absolutely. I insist upon its literal volume and vapors, for however hard I try I can be sure of nothing else in the world but this&#x2013;the fact of her final breath, the merest trace of it lingering in the room like snow or sunlight, burning, freezing against my sealed eyelids and saying: open, open. (Shields, 1993/2008: 40)</p></blockquote> <p_after_extract>The exhalation is the start of the story. She creates it with poetic force. The 'wingbeat' gives the sound and the feeling of breath, of a slight edge of fear, of taking flight, of vertigo. The 'volume and the vapors' give us the sense of smoke, of the space that the story needs to unfold, opening up in front of us.</p_after_extract> <p>Even within the body of this paragraph there is the determined bringing together of discordant, opposite ingredients. The large and the small, signified by the world (huge, overwhelming) bumped up against 'the merest trace' of breath and a newborn's eyelids (tiny, fragile). The cold and the hot&#x2013;snow and sunlight. A beginning and an ending&#x2013;the last breath is the end of Mercy's life but the start of Daisy's. That opening is magically described in the command given by the narrator to the baby's 'sealed eyelids' and she speaks them out loud, in direct speech, so we can hear them, 'open, open.' It is the perfect beginning, and the perfect ending also. </p> <p>So much for the art of mixing elements together. It can be seen that it is not only a question of selecting the ingredients that will cling to each other, but also it is that old alchemists' trick of applying pressure: leaning down hard on the pestle as it grinds the ingredients even finer to get to the detail and to create the forces of attraction which will combine the elements, and provide the exhalation, to create the genesis of the story.</p> <p>In <i>What The Children Saw</i>, I am only halfway to creating the ironic bond between my two sets of children. Then it occurs to me&#x2013;what if, on one side of the graveyard, there is an only child, without siblings, but with plenty of grandparents, while on the other side you have three siblings, who have each other, but no grandparents? </p> <p>I have gathered together some new ingredients for the opening sequence of <i>What The Children Saw</i>. I will not open with the church porch, or the graveyard, or the children in their homes. This material might be thrown away, or it might come later.</p> <p>Instead, I am mixing the ingredients with an eye on how they will bind together. On each side, the one party has what the other lacks: Megan lacks siblings but has eight grandparents (because they have divorced and remarried); and the siblings lack grandparents but have each other. I will begin the story by choosing incidents that will illustrate this ironic bond: it is Easter day, and I call into play the Easter egg as a symbol of resurrection. I want to write this out, to see if it will stick.</p> <blockquote><p>It was Easter <i>Sunday</i>; and games were forbidden. An unearthly quiet hung over both houses&#x2013;no running feet, no slamming doors&#x2013;and Megan went to wait for her grandparents at the spot where they would park their cars. She was joined by the other three children who came down their own driveway: Emma rolling like a boulder, the slap of each footfall marking her out, and the Billies like spiders with their legs and arms moving continually.</p><p>'Happy Easter,' said Emma to Megan. </p> <p>'Hey, and you. Happy Easter,' said Megan.</p> <p>The Billies scrambled up to find a hiding place in the rhododendron bushes, while Megan and Emma waited more conspicuously on the pavement, meandering back and forth. </p> <p>A small red car dragged its exhaust pipe along the ground like a broken, metallic tail. The Billies, their limbs threaded among the rhododendron's branches, shrank back, not to be seen. Emma stayed where she was, with Megan. She only climbed substantial trees, and anyway she didn't ever care to be hidden.</p> <p>When the vehicle stopped Megan leaned through the driver's window to greet the occupants, before they climbed out to examine the broken exhaust pipe. There was nothing they could do. They opened the boot and took hold of two Easter eggs and handed them to Megan, who found that Emma was at her shoulder, breathing heavily. Emma took the eggs off her, one by one, and shook them, to hear the answering rattle which told her they had sweets inside, before she politely handed them back.</p> <p>David and Ben, obscured in the leafy shadows, also measured the size of the Easter eggs, the colour and extravagance of the wrappings, their apparent weight.</p> <p>Megan escorted her grandparents up the driveway at a slow, slow pace, while the others remained behind. In a few minutes she returned and with her she brought three mini-eggs, as consolation for the others. Emma and Ben rubbed and picked at the silver wrapping which clung to the sweaty chocolate until they could pop them in their mouths. David saved his for later, when the others would have finished.</p> <p>There was an interlude, which dragged on while the next pair of grandparents failed to arrive. Nothingy sorts of things happened: Ben tried to dig a hole but David stopped him. David climbed to the fourth branch of the copper beech. Megan complained that her feet hurt. Emma folded and folded again the scrap of silver paper which had encased the mini-egg she'd been given. If it were a magic egg, it would reappear when you rubbed the paper between your palms like this ...  it would be good as new; she could unwrap it again, eat it, once more rub the silver paper in her hands and hey-presto, there'd be another, and again she'd eat …</p></blockquote>  <h2>3. Separating out</h2> <p1>We have looked at ingredients mixed together, but what about the opposite? Alchemy provides not only for mixing together, but also for separation, for dissociation, segregation&#x2013;the pressure applied in the opposite direction to keep elements apart. 'Towards the effecting of works, all that man can do is to put together or put asunder natural bodies. The rest is done by Nature working within' (Bacon, 1905: 259).</p1> <p>Strikingly, in the first 40 pages of <i>The Stone Diaries</i>, the alchemy of segregation is brought to bear on the business of the pregnancy. Carol Shields has stormed in disguised as Daisy and with none of the many declarations of truth or untruth that she gives to other matters she pushes apart the two most important strands in this part of the story: the pregnancy, and the parents' knowledge of the pregnancy. Mercy does not have a clue she is pregnant, therefore neither does Cuyler. And yet she is about to give birth. It is the reason, of course, Carol Shields has made her so fat, in order to construct the logic of this invention, so that we might believe such an incredible thing. </p> <p>Why has she kept this knowledge of the pregnancy from her characters, but allowed it to us? </p> <p>First, because it brings dramatic irony into play, which has an adhesive quality in narrative, as in life. When the information possessed by us, the reader, is greater than that of the characters in the story, it creates in us a sense of privilege. It has a delicious narcissistic quality, this spell that is cast when dramatic irony is summoned. We can assume the all-seeing, all-knowing presence of a God; we can feel ourselves, irrationally, more clever than the characters ...  It creates an area within this story that we have earned by our understanding, by our perception, our prescience. It appears exclusive to us because the characters in the story are excluded. Dramatic irony also creates forward impetus&#x2013;it heavily tilts the story, because we wish to hurry the story along so that we can arrive at the moment when the characters find out what we already know. It is a rich narrative gift and it must be delivered silently, without our being told. There are other narrative conceits that Carol Shields cheerfully admits to but not this one, because if she does so we will see that we are not God, after all&#x2013;she is&#x2013;and our pleasure would be diminished.</p> <p>Mercy and her own pregnancy are kept apart in order to ferment dramatic irony, but there is a second reason for separating them out: Carol Shields wishes to create what would be called in the vocabulary of the alchemist an explosion. In the language of the novelist it might be described as a surprise.</p> <p>It works by sleight of hand (the skills of a magician are necessary to the work of the alchemist) and the prerequisite to this particular sleight of hand is the keeping of those two elements apart: the pregnancy, and the parents' knowledge of the pregnancy. </p> <p>This is how it works. Carol Shields has mixed together two characters: the male, Cuyler, mounts the female copiously, energetically, and the female … well, submits. Mercy's stomach is filled with food, and pain, and flatulence, and a baby&#x2013;our narrator Daisy. Gradually, we become aware&#x2013;since it is never mentioned&#x2013;that Mercy does not know she is pregnant, and neither does Cuyler. Not even today, on the day of the birth of a baby that purportedly will live long enough to write this book, do they know. We are allowed to understand that there is a baby in that vast stomach because it is the baby herself who is telling us the story of the circumstances of her birth. </p> <p>As Mercy puts aside the Malvern pudding, as she leans over the table with her first contractions, with the hysterical calling for help of the old Jew, and with Cuyler's sunny, carefree walk home from work, we are involved in the construction of a surprise for Mercy and a surprise for Cuyler, and for the neighbouring Flett family ...  a surprise for everyone except us: that a baby will arrive soon. Daisy is about to be born. We, the readers, are gleeful at the prospect of seeing the explosion. But, and here is the sleight of hand, while Carol Shields appears to amaze and delight us with the delivery of this surprise to these characters (and so we are watching, transfixed), she is, meanwhile, delivering a different explosion to us, the reader. </p> <p>That explosion is the death of Mercy. The detonation goes off right under our noses.</p> <p>The others have had some intimation, a warning, that something is up. Mercy has the terrific bouts of pain. The old Jew has run for the doctor. The Flett woman has gone over to help. But we are to walk in on the scene&#x2013;what we know will be this startling appearance of a baby&#x2013;and for this moment the author puts us in the company of the least forewarned, the most to-be-surprised among the cast of characters: Cuyler Goodwill, the husband so desperately, erotically in love with his wife, and the man who is already dreaming of children filling a larger, warmer, more brightly lit house than this one he's walking into. He is: </p> <blockquote><p> ...  hungry <i>for the supper</i> already prepared, eager for whatever tenderness the evening will bring. His small dark face and sinewy body burst through his back door, the tune he has been whistling dying on his lips as he falls upon this scene of chaos, his house with its unanticipated unbearable human crowding, a strange sharp scent rising to his nostrils, and a high, rhythmic cry of lamentation&#x2013;where is this coming from, where?&#x2013;these terrifying vowel sounds, iii-yyeeee, spiralling upward and joining the derangement of linen and of air, at the center of which lies his wife&#x2013;on the blood drenched kitchen couch, its gathered cretonne cover&#x2013;my mother, her mountainous body stilled, her eyes closed. (Shields, 1993/2008: 38) </p></blockquote> <p_after_extract>'<i>Stilled, her eyes closed</i>' … Bang, goes the detonation. It is so close up. The body 'stilled, her eyes closed' is the first shockwave, because we are expecting tears in those eyes, and the frightened smile of the new mother. Instead, Mercy is dead? And then: </p_after_extract> <blockquote><p>'eclampsia,' Dr Spears says solemnly, pulling a sheet&#x2013;no, not a sheet but a tablecloth&#x2013;up over her face, and staring at her father with severity. 'Almost certainly eclampsia'. (Shields, 1993/2008: 38)</p></blockquote> <p_after_extract>The doctor's voice says, 'eclampsia' whereas it should be saying, 'It's a girl.' The sheet not as it should be, drawn around Mercy's enormous breasts to protect her modesty, but instead drawn up all the way over her face, in the common gesture signifying death.</p_after_extract>  <p>A cliché is used because this detonation needs to be quick, and sure. The writer pretends to correct herself&#x2013;'not a sheet, no, a tablecloth ...  '&#x2013;and with this correction she stamps her authority on the text. We have been smartly smacked in the face. Carol Shields has shown us who is in control&#x2013;she is. We are ready to believe every word she tells us.</p>  <p>Thus she demonstrates that we must look for opportunities for separation if we want to create dramatic irony and invigorate the alchemy of our narrative.</p> <p>In <i>What The Children Saw</i>, the girls will make a deal. Megan is an only child, and Emma will lend her two brothers to Megan, to play with for three hours. In exchange, Emma asks for half of Megan's second-largest Easter egg. If we keep the knowledge of this deal secret from the boys (the Billies as I have decided to call them), then the alchemy will begin to simmer:</p> <blockquote><p>Emma and Megan drifted together, as if by accident. The billies, a little way off, could hear the girls' quiet, mysterious murmuring without being able to make out what they were saying. </p></blockquote> <p>'Two hours,' mumbled Emma.</p> <p>'Three?'</p> <p>'How <i>big</i> then?'</p> <p>Megan's instinct was to be generous, to give to Emma all her Easter eggs, her whole heart and mind and all her possessions, her life on a plate, because she wanted nothing less in return from Emma, but it didn't work like that. It took her some moments of staring blankly, kicking the pavement, tugging at her clothes, to recover. 'Not the very biggest,' she replied, 'but you can choose half, of any one you like <i>below</i> that. Just half of it.'</p> <p>'For three hours?'</p> <p>'Yes. Alone, though. Without you.'</p> <p>'The whole egg.'</p> <p>'No, half.'</p> <p>'Deal?'</p> <p>'For half.'</p> <p>'Deal?'</p> <p>'Yes, deal,' Megan echoed back. The two girls touched their closed fists which did for a handshake. It wasn't as complicated and intimate as the handshake Emma performed with her brothers: after the closed fists they would slap their palms, top and bottom, clasp each other's fingers, twiddle their thumbs. It rankled with Megan to be excluded from this ritual. 'Don't tell them, though,' she said, as Emma wandered off.</p> <p>'Course not.'  </p> <p>'Really, don' t tell them.'</p> <p>'I won't.'</p> <p>'Promise.'</p> <p>'I won't tell them.'</p> <p_after_extract>The Billies do not know they have been sold. This is my separation. However, it strikes me that an opportunity exists to create the separation in a different way, to lever apart different elements of the story, to greater effect. If Emma breaks her word and tells the boys about the deal (and she always tells them, because this happens all the time) then it is Megan whom we feel sorry for. Our sense of pity for Megan as an only child will be compounded by our witnessing the boys' knowledge that she's had to pay for them to play with her. </p_after_extract> <blockquote><p> David and Ben were kicking each other's shins. Emma pulled them apart. 'Megan's got you both for three hours,' she said brutally. </p></blockquote> <p>'When?'</p> <p>'This afternoon.' </p> <p>'How much?'</p> <p>'One… one bite. Each. A small one.'</p> <p>They stared at her, distrustful.</p> <p_after_extract>The mixing together of ingredients: siblings, an only child, Easter eggs, grandparents. The separation of ingredients: Megan not knowing that the boys know she has paid for their company. Both are designed to work towards an exhalation: the birth of the story, created by Megan's idea for a game she might play with the Billies. And here I need to foreshadow it, and create in the text the genesis of the game: </p_after_extract> <blockquote><p>Megan was alone again, and back in the rut of waiting ...  Grandparents were a bore. The others had romantic notions about them, but if they had some of their own, they'd know. She fell into a reverie. What would she do with the billies, later? Three hours, she had, for something good. There was, suddenly, a picture in her mind: the sideboard in the dining room in Emma's house, its cupboard door opening, and the dark recess within&#x2013;the unknown. Numerous strange objects there ...  a funeral urn, she was sure. Or more than one. Her own hand, white as a ghost's, reached in… </p></blockquote> <p>How many stories started with a door opening, she wondered? Millions.</p> <p>She pushed the idea away&#x2013;no. If she suggested such a thing, the billies would think she was mad. </p> <h2>4. The art of logic</h2> <p1>We can do anything we choose with our characters. We are Gods playing with their fates. But we have to be able to suspend the disbelief of our readers, and in its place create belief, if we want to enchant them. To create such a belief, we have to attend to the logic, however fantastic the scenario. (The absence of logic, especially, should be logical.) In <i>What The Children Saw</i>, if I am to create belief in the story, it should make sense.</p1> <p>We are so thoroughly caught up in the alchemy of Carol Shields' detonation only because of the lavish attention she gives to the logic of the situation. In the case of Mercy Goodwill's death, Shields' embrace of logic is proven if we follow upstream the moment-by-moment identification of two separate channels of cause and effect. When we follow Cuyler into the room, the sights and sounds that Carol Shields arranges for us are equally logical in a death scene and a birth scene: the chaos, the strange smell, the cry of lamentation, the 'iii-yeee', the mess of linen, the bloodied couch ...  it is only when we reach that word 'stilled,' and we see Mercy's eyes not open but closed, that we experience the explosion and realize this is her death bed. In a trice, unthinking, we trace the logic backwards from the word 'eclampsia'. The sights and sounds that Carol Shields has described in order to warn us of Daisy's imminent birth are the same sights and sounds that will make sense given the fact, now, of Mercy's <i>death</i>. The sheer size of Mercy is a central plank in this logic. It is the reason why she might not know of her own pregnancy; and eclampsia, the reason the author gives for Mercy's death, is a condition commonly ascribed to overweight mothers. Mercy's refusal to go to the doctor is another visible strut in the construction of this logic: eclampsia is diagnosed via high blood pressure and a visit to the doctor would easily have told Mercy she was in danger. The pain, the flatulence ...  all these are symptomatic of eclampsia <i>and</i> pregnancy. Because we find that everything fits, because the logic is evident, we therefore approve, and believe.</p> <p>The romantically named Arnoldus de Nova Villa, alchemist and philosopher, correctly divined the importance of the relationship between alchemy and logic. ' ...  therefore no body should approach to this art [alchemy], unlesse he has heard before some Logick, which teaches to distinguish truth from falsehood, and withall the naturall art which teaches the things of nature, and the property of the elements, otherwise he troubles his minde and body and life in vaine' (De Nova Villa, 1986).  </p> <p>In order to underpin the bluster and the trickery of the alchemical process, and in order to create his effect, the alchemist must engage in a love-affair with logic. It might be only a semblance of logic but it must appear watertight.</p> <p>The magician, just like the alchemist, must be a devotee of logic, but must work towards the opposite effect. The magician knows that to pull a rabbit out of a hat is not enough&#x2013;is nothing, in fact&#x2013;without obscuring, or masking, the logic of how it got there. The aim of the magician is to deliver a surprise and arouse in the audience the reaction, 'I don't believe it! What an incredible trick!'. The novelist must deliver the surprise and at the same time sponsor in the reader the opposite reaction, 'I believe it, I <i>see</i> ...  '. This is the critical difference between the magician and the writer-as-alchemist. For the writer, the evidence of logic&#x2013;its display, the sight of it&#x2013;is essential if we are to believe the story as being 'real'. </p> <p>It is not that we do not understand that the most blinding coincidences and accidents of fate happen in real life. They happen all the time. But a trick, a twist without logic, in fiction, has no currency because it is the easy way out for an author and does nothing for us but unmask the author-as-puppeteer, whereas for the magician, it <i>is</i> his currency and it <i>is</i> the difficult thing to do.</p> <p>The novelist has to do as much work to show the logic that delivers the surprise as the magician does to obscure it. And yet to show the logic will give away the surprise. This is the anomaly that the fiction writer must deal with, in one way or another.</p> <h2>5. Still on the art of logic</h2> <p1>In <i>The Secret Scripture</i> (2008) by Sebastian Barry there are two detonations; one of them works and one of them does not. The detonation that fails, I am willing to guess, cost him the Booker Prize of 2008 and was responsible for the extraordinary sight of the Costa prize chairman explaining that they were making this book their winner even though it had 'something wrong with the ending.' </p1> <p><i>The Secret Scripture</i> is narrated by two different voices: that of Roseanne Clear, a very old lady who has been falsely incarcerated in a lunatic asylum ever since she gave birth to an illegitimate baby in 1957, and that of Dr Grene, who is in charge of Roscommon Regional Mental Hospital, where she has ended up. The hospital is in the process of closing down, and throughout the story Grene finds out more and more about his elderly patient, how she was ill-served by her family and sectioned when she was in fact perfectly sane. He finds out about the infant she bore, as she crouched in 'a nest of boulders' (Barry, 2008: 262) in the middle of a storm. The newborn was taken from her breast while she slept, out in the open. She awoke and 'there was blood and the skin and cord and the placenta. I started to my feet. I was as dizzy and weak as a newborn foal myself. Where was my baby?' (Barry, 2008: 264).</p> <p>No one knows what happened to the baby. Dr Grene is the only person who wants to take the trouble to find out.</p> <p>Towards the end of the book Dr Grene travels to an orphanage in Bexhill, Surrey, to track down the child who was taken from Roseanne's breast so long ago. He is put in a room with the relevant documents. 'The child's name was William Clear, born of Roseanne Clear, waitress ...  The child was given to Mr and Mrs Grene of Padstow, Cornwall, in 1945' (Barry, 2008: 289).</p> <p>He himself <i>is</i> that child&#x2013;this is the detonation. Immediately, quick as a tidal surge, we reach upstream for a seam of logic that brought us here ...  but we search in vain. There is nothing. Sebastian Barry thought to pull off this detonation, this surprise, in the same way as might a magician, by obscuring the logic. His argument for doing it in this way might have been that it is how life happens: sometimes we get these vulnerable, uncertain places in the unfolding of events, and a novel that is true-to-life must therefore contain them. </p> <p>Another reason might have been that to have shown any part of the logic in advance would have spoilt the surprise, but that is exactly what makes it so difficult to pull off a good surprise in fiction. It is sleight of hand that must obscure the logic, it is not enough simply to leave it out. So, that is the art required: to disguise it in such a way that we see it, but do not see it. </p> <p>In true life the surprise would have been gratifying. We would have shaken our heads in wonder at it. In fiction we feel cheated. We can see the author's hand working the characters. The illusion-making spell is broken. It is such a big trick that we feel doubly resentful. </p> <p>In truth, this coincidence, which we would have accepted if it had been positioned at the beginning of the story, was of no consequence. The enormous power and beauty of this novel has already been dealt to us magnificently for 288 pages, with only a dozen left to go. It does not matter who the child is. For the duration of a few lines the bubble bursts, but any reader with a heart will mend the bubble themselves and carry on.</p> <p>The artist and writer Sebastian Horsley purposefully travelled half way across the world to have himself crucified and did not die but merely fainted. Instead, at home, in his bed, he died by accident. He loomed over me once at the junction of Wardour Street and Meard St, his tie a huge eggshell blue triangle at his neck, the suit of clothes a rich silver, and he put it succinctly, 'The difference between fiction and non-fiction is that fiction has to make sense.' </p> <p>Non-fiction writing has its logic-work done for it, and does not need to add up, whereas fiction-writing requires not only the invention of its logic, and that the logic should appear watertight (especially if the story proposes a nonsense world), but for its full powers to be invoked a novel also requires the author's delightful manipulation of logic on behalf of the reader&#x2013;an artful display of logic.</p> <p>This requires me to insist even further on the importance of logic.</p> <h2>6. Still more on the art of logic</h2> <p1>The work of the alchemist Francis Bacon was wholly geared towards 'the inquisition of Causes, and the production of Effects ... and I know it well, that there is an intercourse between Causes and Effects ... ascending from experiments to the invention of Causes, and descending from Causes to the invention of new experiments' (Bacon, 1905: 92). Arriving from a different direction, I have come to appreciate the powerful influence of logic, and the manipulation of logic, on the art of composing fiction.</p1> <p>I sometimes walk at night on the moorland that stretches from the gates of my house for a distance of forty miles or so westward. When I return, and come down off the moor to approach what I think of (since to leave the moor is somewhat like arriving safely at the shore) as the inland pastures, where hedgerow, and wall, and tree cover are all different thicknesses of shadow, I am alerted to the presence of three or four owls at work in their various territories. They will be barn owls or little owls, and the screeches signify they are protecting territory and hunting: the terrifying sound is to frighten mice and voles, and make them move in the grass. </p> <p>An owl's eyes have developed in a specific way to help them catch their prey at night. They are large, like massive tubular cameras, so big that they cannot swivel in their sockets as ours can (instead their heads turn). The iris has an extensive range, shrinking the entrance to the pupil to a pinprick but at night opening to allow the entire circumference of the eye to capture light. Their retinas have very few colour-sensitive cones, and this makes room for a higher density of the rods that detect black and white, which are more effective in gathering light. They have three eyelids: one for blinking, another which closes during sleep, and a third for cleaning. All these features have evolved to allow the eye to see in the dark almost as well as in the day. </p> <p>The flatness of their faces, and the distance between their eyes, allows them to judge depth of field and more accurately locate their prey. The way they bob their heads up and down and from side to side increases this effect. They are judging distance, depth&#x2013;position. </p> <p>They are perfectly adapted to see, from a long way off, that movement in the grass. </p> <p>They swoop silently, the tip of each feather is soft as down to allow noiseless flight. The owl is moving fast towards its prey but their eyes become less useful now, because they are adapted for long sight. The picture begins to blur.</p> <p>The owl's sense of hearing takes over. The barn owl, in particular has a pronounced facial disc, like saucers around the eyes. They act like radar dishes to gather sound into the ear apertures. The apertures themselves (situated just behind the radar dishes) are asymmetrical, one side higher than the other, to allow for up-and-down location of the sound. If the vole moves backwards an inch, the sound comes from an inch lower, and the sound will arrive quicker at the right ear. If the vole darts forwards and the sound comes from an inch higher than before, the left ear hears it a fraction earlier. The owl has developed extraordinary ability in this; it can measure a difference in time between its ears of 0.00003 seconds.</p> <p>Side to side movement is measured in the same way. The combination of signals is processed instantly in the owl's brain, on the wing. The owl keeps its facial disk pointing towards the sound, and follows. They have developed pinpoint spatial awareness from the auditory signal.</p> <p>Close to its prey, the owl stalls and reaches forward with its talons while keeping its facial disk precisely aimed at the sound. </p> <p>For the last couple of feet, the owl <i>closes its eyes</i>. Their sense of sound is wholly accurate (and it allows them to catch prey under snow or under leaves), and this closing of their eyes just before impact implies&#x2013;to my mind&#x2013;a delicious gastronomy, a sense of bliss in its capturing food, that must come, surely, as a reward at this point.</p> <p>As I walk home in the moonlight I hear two or three different owls, all up to the same thing. It stirs one's attachment to a landscape, that it is shared with such creatures.</p> <p>The owls' confabulation of sound and vision to locate the slightest movement in the grass is an example of the way in which an  individual species has developed specific skills in order to make use of the world that surrounds it.</p> <p>We, mankind, have won extraordinary dominion over our surroundings, so what is our species-specific skill? In what area of the brain have we developed extraordinary ability? The answer is logic. </p> <p>If the blood is poisoned and heats up in a fever, then we find out why, and stop it. If the car breaks down we will find out why and fix it. If the colour blue is too expensive to produce we will find a cheaper way to make it. If water is the only liquid that expands when frozen then we will take measures to protect ourselves from the damaging effects. If my wife's eyes are downcast when receiving her birthday gift I must try and guess why. If a crumb of sodium buzzes around on the surface of water, we will do everything in our power to find out why and make use of it. Our every waking moment is, and has been&#x2013;ever since the suffix '<i>sapiens</i>' was added to our species nomenclature&#x2013;dedicated to the enquiry into (and the engineering of) cause and effect, or logic.</p> <p>Francis Bacon put a God-made-man at the centre of his universe and thought that everything was arranged to suit him, but I would put it the other way around, Man developed extraordinary skill at logic and thereby learned to use animals and plants of every kind to feed himself, provide shelter, clothing, food, medicine, to give him comfort and pleasure and to reduce his work. He learned to trap the wind in his sails and he altered the course of water to drive his mills. He worked out how the stars could give him directions, worked out how predicting the weather might help his farms. </p> <p>All our science, art, observation, psychology, all our design, is the operation of logic's pulleys and levers. </p> <p>It is one of the two skills uniquely well-developed in our species (I would like to mention the other one later): we observe a change, the slightest whisper of a change, and we race to find out why, and what caused that change, and what the consequences will be. This attribute is so finely tuned in our species that any change, however small, is, for us, <i>a movement in the grass</i>. </p> <p>We ceaselessly measure how things change and why. We measure the extra pound of weight on our waist, or another grey hair. We measure the increase or decrease in our wealth. We measure the smallest alteration in our affection for our friends or family, as well as the apparent changes in their affection for us, and we fret about the reasons. Our brain is wired to measure change and the reasons for change and what we might do about it. Logic is how we work, and why we win, why we eat.  </p> <p>De Nova Villa was right and the novelist, charged with bringing the art of alchemy to the writing of fiction, is wise not only to deal in logic but to develop a great love for it, a passionate engagement with cause and effect, with change, and an understanding of how it might be manipulated and beautifully displayed in order to seize the attention of the reader. The skilful novelist takes delight in creating the movement in the grass that will transfix the reader.</p> In <i>Wuthering Heights</i> (1847), Emily Brontë gives us, first of all, Lockwood's account of Heathcliff: a violent, cold-hearted, disappointed man who murdered his own son and enslaved his daughter-in-law. The author then conjures a storm in order to force Lockwood into staying the night so she might describe him&#x2013;quickly&#x2013;going up to the attic bedroom and discovering Catherine's diary. This diary gives a different view of Heathcliff. As a boy, he was neither cold-hearted, nor disappointed, nor murderous, nor a bully. When the child diary-writer Catherine throws her book into the fireplace we learn that 'Heathcliff kicked his to the same place' (Brontë, 1847: 22). He is copying her; far from being an assertive bully he is a willing passenger.  The diary continues. They hide together after she 'just fastened our pinafores together, and hung them up for a curtain' (Brontë, 1847: 22). The child Heathcliff suggests to the child Catherine, 'that we should appropriate the dairy woman's cloak, and have a scamper on the moors, under its shelter. A pleasant suggestion' (Brontë, 1847: 22). The child Heathcliff wants to please the child Catherine; in his love for her he is generous, optimistic, adventurous. And this is in spite of the fact that Heathcliff himself is ill treated, 'Poor Heathcliff!' Catherine's diary continues, 'Hindley calls him a vagabond, and won't let him sit with us, nor eat with us anymore; and he says, he and I must not play together, and threatens to turn him out of the house if we break his orders' (Brontë, 1847: 24). <p>Two different Heathcliffs are put in front of us, side by side: a vicious, 'unnmannerly wretch' (Brontë, 1847: 17) in his middle age, and an innocent, imaginative, loving child. It is a big gap&#x2013;a big change. We are well and truly alerted. We swoop on this, we demand to know the logic of how and why such a change took place. How the one Heathcliff became the other. We begin to make our guesses; we start work immediately. The remaining 360 pages is our flight, at the end of which we have that full and complete understanding: Heathcliff changed to such an extent not so much due to his ill-treatment at the hands of others but because his perfect love for Catherine (when she unfairly changed into a different type of person) was rejected. A brute like Heathcliff becomes a romantic hero for millions of readers because the logic is compelling: the scale of the change in Heathcliff, the extent to which he has become vicious, is the exact measure of the depth and ferocity of his love for Catherine&#x2013;a girl who turned to dust in his fingers. </p> <p>Emily Brontë engineered this section of the novel when Lockwood is narrator to be directly adjacent to the section when Catherine's diary is the narrator, and in this way she skips from one time to another and from one point-of-view to another in order to give us, at the outset of the novel, the 'effect' in 'cause-and-effect' and to a reader this is magical. It is the movement in the grass. We demand to know the cause so that we can join it to the effect. We swoop on the rest of the story, eat it up. </p> <p>Ford Madox Ford, in <i>The Good Soldier</i> (1915), creates layer after layer of effect and cause in a similar way&#x2013;each layer creating differences in our perception of his characters&#x2013;by manipulating the point of view of the narration and by using his 'fireside' narrator to skip back and forth in time. It is the same manipulation of time and point-of-view, but executed in a more subtle and refined way.</p> <p>In the analogy following this one, I will describe how a number of literary novelists use the same technique to construct an objective, a forward progression in their stories. This is what fiction-writing is: orchestrating a dance with logic; it is a display. </p> <p>Monty Roberts, the rodeo champion, race-horse trainer and horse-whisperer, describes in his autobiography <i>The Man Who Listens To Horses</i>, how the dominant mare in a wild herd would discipline badly-behaved youngsters by aggressively driving them outside the group. Standing alone, some distance away, the youngster would become aware of the danger of his position. Predators would be looking to pick off any animal left unprotected, outside the group. The adolescent would submit, and beg to be let back in.</p> <p>This psychology accounted for various inexplicable behaviours in horses. Monty's observations furnished him with a special ability to understand them and manipulate their behaviour. He described them as 'into-pressure' creatures.</p> <p>I would say that we, as a species, are 'into-logic' creatures. To give us first of all the 'effect' part of 'cause and effect' works by driving us out of the logic of the story, and our powerful instinct, as Homo sapiens, is to 'turn into' it, to find our way back and understand it. </p> <p>It is the favourite technique of mystery writers. To leave us out of the chain of cause-and-effect means a question is aroused in our minds&#x2013;or a series of questions. We have noticed sudden alterations in our situation, a change in everyone around us, and our powerful instinct, our continual exercising of logic, compels us to find out how and why these changes happened. We must push our way back into the narrative. We can only succeed by continuing to read.</p> <p><i>Wuthering Heights</i> is successful, is golden, because Brontë is adept at the alchemy of fiction-writing, the spell-making, the enchantment. She conjures ingredients, and brings together or separates them, and she leans hard on her text, and she manipulates logic in order to display it in such a way as to enchant us. As a result we are given the impression of a very certain, truthful reality taking us (as willing passengers) for a ride. A profusion of specific, chosen details gives the piece its energy, and the heady language is its music. We forgive the chaos of the differing points of view and the unlikely child's diary. In the text we see and feel the truth, expressed with beauty and powerful invention and so the base metal is transformed into gold. </p> </div><div>Writing exercise no. 6:  'Gathering' <p1_exercise>Start work: gather a pile of ingredients: the incidents, the setting, the characters, the buildings, the animals. Some of these materials will be used and others won't. Some will be used and thrown away. Some will have to be specifically sought out, half way through. </p1_exercise> <p_exercise>To 'gather' these ingredients might involve buying or borrowing books, or it might entail foreign travel, or perhaps you will only have to sit with a pen and notebook and remember events from your past. It might involve consulting car manuals or observing the habits of a wild animal on Youtube, or writing down observations on how people behave when they're waiting for trains. It might involve an in-depth exploration of medical advances in the 17th century, or the conceiving of a river system set in the future, when there is zero rainfall. Whichever is the case, it's the significant and attractive details that will offer the richest rewards.</p_exercise> <p_exercise>You can't do enough 'gathering'&#x2013;your novel will change and develop; it will find its way of giving its pleasures to your readers, but its success will depend on a rich gathering process. </p_exercise></div></story>
